Guide to the Ernie O'Malley Papers AIA.060
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
- Series II. Correspondence: Incoming, 1922-1956
  - Leventhal, Con (Professor, Trinity College), Feb 7, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Little, Con W., Jan 5, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Longhnane, Anne, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - [MJ] (unkown); Mae Tobin, Limerick; to Ernie O'Malley in Hare Park Jail, Ju 10, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Macardle, Dorothy (author), May 22, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - MacCarville, Eileen McGrane (Professor of English, UCD), Jul 8, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - MacGreevy, Thomas (poet, author, Director National Gallery), 1940, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - MacManus, M.J. (Editor, Irish Press), 1936-1937 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - MacNiece, Heidi and Louis, 1947-1949 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Mayer, Therese (La France Libre), 1947-1950 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - McCrossan, Helen (Mrs. Preson McGrassan), 1930 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - McGlynn, Mick (McGlynn Travel Bureau), 1933 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - McGrail, Jean, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - McGuinness, Norah (artist), 1936 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - McHugh, Roger (UCD Dramatic Society; Professor of English), 1945 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - McMahon, Bryan (storyteller, author), 1947-1952 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - McSwiney, Mary (sister of Terence), Nov 28, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Mellquist, Jerome (friend from Yaddo), Sep 2, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Millburn, George, 1932-1933 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Miller, Otto (Wick Miller Soutwest Indian Crafts, San Ysidro, NM), 1932 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Mooney, Ria (actress), Nov 1, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Moore, Owen (military comrade), Oct 30, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Murphy, Delia (Mrs. T.J. McKiernan), 1941 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Murphy, Fr. Miceal (Michael), 1946-1948 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Murphy, Maigread (Mrs. Seamus Murphy), 1951-1952 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - [Nib, E.] (unknown) to Ernie O'Malley in jail, Jun 10, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Nolan, Dan (Editor, The Kerryman), 1952 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Noyk, Michael (solicitor for Ernie O'Malley; includes letter from Sean MacBride in re O'Mally v O'Mally), 1946-1974 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - O'Broichain, Eoin (University Cork Dublin Democratic Society), Mar 19, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - O'Donnell, Peadar (Editor, The Bel l), 1947-1951 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - O'Donoghue, Florrie, Oct 16, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - O'Donovan, James L., 1923, 1936-1937 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - O'Faolain, Sean (author), 1939-1947 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - O'Flaherty, Liam (author), Jul 16, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - O'Laoighaire, LIam (Irish Film Society), 1937 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - O'Riann, Proinnsius, 1932-1933 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - O'Sullivan, Seamus (Editor, Dublin Magazine), 1940, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - O'Sullivan, Sean (artist), 1942-1944 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Otis, Raymond (Writers' Editions), 1935 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Piper, John (English painter), Feb 19, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Poetry Magazine (Chicago) (item from Chicago archives, photocopy), undated (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - [Proinnsias] (Frank, unknown), Fr., circa 1924 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Quinn [Frank], 1930 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Radio Eireann (includes correspondence from Francis McManus), 1937-1952 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Rakoczi, Basil (artist; leader White Stag School of Art, Ireland, 1940-1947), 1945 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Raleigh, John and Beatrice, 1944, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Raleigh, Peggy (Ernie O'Malley's goddaughter; daughter of John Raleigh) [no page 2], May 1945 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - Reid, Nano, Dec 8, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - ni Riann, Mairin Bean (Mrs. James Ryan), Jun 13, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Riardon, Eileen, circa 1940-1950 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Rich & Cowan Publishers and Exporters, 1936-1951 (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - Rolt, David (artist, did portrait of Ernie O'Malley), 1947, undated (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Rookh, Lalla, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Rothenstein, John (Director, Tate Gallery) also letter from Geroge Nicholson, 1945-1946 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Ryan, Desmond (author), Dec 14, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Saenz, Moises, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Salkeld, Cecil and Mrs. (artist), 1945, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Schwartz, Anne Powers (novelist, 1913-1987), 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - Sheehy, Michael (Offaly comrade), Jun 21, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Sheehy-Skeffington, Hanna, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - Sommerville-Largo, Sammy, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - Stevenson, Philip (Ted; Yaddo), 1932 (Box 4, Folder 86)
  - Steward, Dorothy, 1930-1938 (Box 4, Folder 87)
  - Strand, Paul, 1932-1956 (Box 4, Folder 88)
  - Stuart, Stan (Limerick comrade), Nov 2, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - Sweeny, James Johnson, 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 90)
  - Sweeney, John "Jack", 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 91)
  - Sykes, Gerald, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 92)
  - Tobin, Eva and Marion (includes photograph of "Eva and Mae Tobin", 1924, 1951, undated (Box 4, Folder 93)
  - Traynor, Oscar (Dublin comrade), Mar 12, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 94)
  - Varney, John, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 95)
  - Villard, Marquita, circa 1933-1935 (Box 4, Folder 96)
  - Vorse, Mary Ellen Heaton, 1932, undated (Box 4, Folder 97)
  - Waddington, Victor (art gallery owner), 1945 (Box 4, Folder 98)
  - Walsh, Roisin (Librarian, Dublin), Oct 14, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 99)
  - Walston, Harry and Catherine (Bob); son William, 1946-1950 (Box 4, Folder 100)
  - Weeks, Edward (Atlantic Monthly Press), 1935 (Box 4, Folder 101)
  - Weston, Edward, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 102)
  - Wilson, Thomas J. (Harvard University Press), 1947 (Box 4, Folder 103)
  - Woods, Robert and Peggy, 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 104)
  - Woods, Tony (Hospitals' Trust), 1936-1954, undated (Box 4, Folder 105)
  - Young, Ella, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 106)
  - Zablodowsky, David (Viking Press), 1935 (Box 4, Folder 107)
  - [Unknown] (Carroll of Chicago), 1934 (Box 4, Folder 108)
  - Various: Christmas Cards, circa 1936-1955 (Box 4, Folder 109)
  - Various: Postcards, 1927-1951 (Box 4, Folder 110)
  - [Unknown] (Ranchi Ottorino D., Counsel to Mrs. Ranchi), 1929 (Box 4, Folder 111)
- Series III. Correspondence: Outgoing, 1922-1956
  Letters from Ernie O'Malley to friends, associates, artists, editors, professors, military comrades, government agencies, solicitors, and other correspondents in Ireland and the United States between the years of 1922 and 1956. Topics in this series range broadly from general greetings to business dealings. Many of the letters provide insight into O'Malley's ailments and failing health resulting from injuries he sustained during his military career. Of special interest are letters O'Malley wrote concerning his work with the Irish Press in the United States and the status of his pension from the Irish government, as well as, transcriptions of letters from O'Malley to Monsignor John Hagan with O'Malley using the alias, Cecil Smyth-Howard, during his European travels in 1925 and 1926. A substantial number of items in this series are photocopies received from various universities and institutions, at the request of Cormac O'Malley, Ernie O'Malley's youngest son. Throughout the course of research on his father Cormac O'Malley also transcribed a considerable number of the letters written by Ernie O'Malley. Those transcriptions have been included with the original or photocopy when available. See accompanying index for a complete listing of correspondents indicating where originals are currently held, as well as, the volume of correspondence associated with each correspondent.
  - Index to Correspondence: Outgoing, 2010 (Box 4, Folder 112)
  - Aikin, Frank, 1928-1932 (Box 4, Folder 113)
  - Ames, Elizabeth (Yaddo), 1932 (Box 4, Folder 114)
  - Beaslia, Piaras, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 115)
  - Brady, Kathleen (Kay), 1925-1926 (Box 4, Folder 116)
  - Breannan, Maurteen (Martin), 1951 (Box 4, Folder 117)
  - Brett, Dorothy, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 118)
  - British and Irish Steam Packet Co., 1938 (Box 4, Folder 119)
  - Childers, Mary Alden Osgood (Mrs. Erskine Childers), 1923-1924 (Box 4, Folder 120)
  - Childers, Mary Alden Osgood (Mrs. Erskine Childers) (see also Subject Files), 1923 (Box 4, Folder 121)
  - Citkowitz-Liber, Rebecca, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 122)
  - Clifford-Comer, Madge (Mrs. Jack Comer), 1924-1937 (Box 4, Folder 123)
  - Comer, Ellis, Dec 30, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 124)
  - Davis, Chester C. (Simpson, Thatcher and Barlett; re expenses for EOM/COM), 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 125)
  - Department of Defence, Mar 1, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 126)
  - DeValera, Eamon, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 127)
  - Fitzgerald, Mabel (from jail), 1921-1924 (Box 4, Folder 128)
  - Ford, John, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 129)
  - Gallagher, Frank, 1926-1954 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Gilchrist, Thomas B., 1947-1950 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Golden, Helen Merriam, 1930-1935 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Golden-Sax, Eithne, 1934-1955 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Hagan, Monsignor John, 1925-1926 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Herbert, Robert (Librarian, Co. Limerick), 1942-1956 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Hughes, Mary (envelope only), undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Humphreys, Sigle (Sheila, Mrs. Donal O'Donoghue), 1922-1931 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Irish Estates (EOM's Irish apartment landlord), Jul 2, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Irish Land Commission, May 23, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Irish Pension Board, 1934-1950 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Kelleher, John V., 1947-1950 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Kelly, [P.J.], Westport, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Kerrigan, Georgette, (Donegal), 1951 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - MacGreevy, Thomas, 1939-1940, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Manahan, Liam, 1950-1953 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - McGrail, Jean (America sculptor, travel writer), 1955-1956 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - McHugh, Patricia "Patsy" (Mrs. Roger McHugh), Sep 22, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - McHugh, Roger, Apr 23, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - McManus, Francis (Radio Eireann), 1952-1953 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Monroe, Harriet ( Poetry Magazine), 1934-1935 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Murphy, Maigread, 1953-1954 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Nolan, Dan ( The Kerryman), Oct 31, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Noyk, Michael, Esq (attorney for Ernie O'Malley), 1950-1953, undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - O'Donovan, James (transcripts of letters), 1936 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - O'Dowd, John, Jul 19, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - O'rahilly, Aodogan and Maureen, Dec 1937 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - O'Reilly, Tom, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - O'Sullivan, Seamus, 1947, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Plunkett, Countess (Mary Josephine), 1923, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Power, George, Dec 19, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Raleigh, John, 1925-1955, undated (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Raleigh, Peggy, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Rothenstein, John (Tate Gallery, London), Oct 26, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Ryan, Desmond, 1936, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Sheehy, Michael, 1951-1956 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Solomons, Estella, 1923 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Somerville-Large, Sammy, May 6, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Stephenson, Dean, circa 9153 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Strand, Paul (papers from Center for Creative Photography Archives, Unversity of Arizona), 1932, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Sunday Press, 1955-1596 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Sweeney, James Johnson and Laura, 1939-1955 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Wall, Mervyn (Radio Eireann), 1953 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Weston, Edward (papers from Center for Creative Photography Archives, Unversity of Arizona), 1929, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 44)
- Series IV. Correspondence: Family, 1914-1957
  Incoming and outgoing correspondence between Ernie O'Malley and members of his family including his mother, siblings, children, wife, in-laws, cousins and others. Also included in this series are letters from family members that were neither addressed to nor written by O'Malley. As in other Correspondence Series, numerous photocopies of originals exist within this series. See index for a complete listing
  - Index to Correspondence: Family, 2010 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Borton, Gertie Kearney, circa 1915-1916 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Hooker, Blanche Ferry (mother-in-law), 1938-1948 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Hooker, Elon Huntington (father-in-law), 1935-1937 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Laithwaite, Sylvia (Ernie O'Malley's first cousin; interesting background on O'Malley), 1930-1945 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Malley, Albert (brother), 1915 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Malley, Cecil and Margaret (brother and sister-in-law), 1943 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Malley, Kathleen (sister), 1935-1942 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Malley, Kevin (brother), 1930-1957 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Malley, Marion (mother, Mrs. Luke Malley), 1922-1946 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Malley, Marion (Mrs. Desmond O'Malley, sister-in-law), 1945-1948 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Malley, Sweetie (sister, Marion), 1947-1948 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Marquand, Adelaide Hooker (sister-in-law), 1936, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - O'Malley, Cathal (son; mostly Ernie O'Malley correspondence), 1939-1957, undated (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - O'Malley, Cathal (son): Diary, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - O'Malley, Cormac (son), 1948-1953, undated (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - O'Malley, Ernie to Helen, Cathal, Etain I (copies), 1942-1955 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - O'Malley, Ernie to Helen, Cathal, Etain I (copies), 1942-1955 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - O'Malley, Etain (daughter), 1945-1956, undated (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - O'Malley, Helen Hooker, 1937-1955 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - O'Malley, Helen Hooker I (copies), 1933-1939 (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - O'Malley, Helen Hooker II (copies), 1933-1939 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Transcriptions of select family correspondence 1933-1956 by Cormac O'Malley, 1933-1956, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 67)
- Series V. Personal, 1912-2006
  Address books, memberships, book slips, inventories, lists, invitations, announcements, school records, memorabilia and other miscellaneous materials covering various events in Ernie O'Malley's life. Throughout the course of his life O'Malley, an avid reader, acquired a vast and diverse personal library. Due to financial hardships during the late 1940s and early 1950s O'Malley was forced to sell a substantial portion of books from his personal library. Card catalogs and inventories in this series reflect the many changes in his personal collection of books before and following the sale. Of special interest is a collection of book slips from the National Library of Ireland, New York Public Library and Newberry Library in Chicago, Illinois documenting the hundreds of books O'Malley read or checked out from each institution during the 1930s. Series is arranged alphabetically by type, generally.
  - Index to Personal, 2010 (Box 6, Folder 1A)
  - Address Books, 1944-1955 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Address Books, 1950-1955 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Catlogue of Printed Books: Southeby & Company, London (2 copies), 1949 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Ernie O'Malley and Helen Hungtington Hooker - scrapbook of articles by and about, Dec 2006 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Inventories of Books, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Inventories of Books - typed and annotated, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Inventories of Books: Missing books, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Inventory of Books: Card catalog slips (inventory of O'Malley book collection) and handwritten Spanish flashcards (5-8 in inventory), undated (Box 30)
  - Inventory of Books: Card catalog slips (inventory of O'Malley book collection) and handwritten Spanish flashcards (5-8 in inventory), undated (Box 31)
  - Inventory of Books: Book slips (National Library of Ireland), circa 1935-1940, covering books EOM was reading on Irish history, literature, drama, poetry, archaeology, early Irish Christian Ireland, European Renaissance art, art generally, military history, geography Book slips (New York Public Library), circa 1932-1935 covering books EOM was reading on Irish literature (JJames, Willima Butler Yeats, Lady Gregory, P Column, etc), history Book slips (Newberry Library, Chicago IL), books EOM was reading while working at the World’s Fair in summer 1933 on Irish/Welsh (Items 5-5, 5-6 5-7), undated (Box 32)
  - Irish Academy of Letters, circa 1946, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Irish Ration Book, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Membership Cards: Sinn Fein (Ernie O'Malley); English Speaking Union Club (Mrs. Ernie O'Malley), 1925, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Nameplate - hand colored (Ernie O'Malley), undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Reading List for [O'Malley] Children, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Results - Annual Examination (Ernie O'Malley): O'Connell School, Dublin, 1912 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Schedule during stay with Golden Family in New Mexico, 1932 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Series VI. Legal, 1921-1957
  The series contains legal documents and clippings relating to Ernie O'Malley between the years of 1923 and 1957. Most materials in this series relate to the legal proceedings between O'Malley and his estranged wife, Helen Hooker O'Malley in 1950. Also included are clippings documenting the libel lawsuit and settlement between Joseph O'Doherty and Ernie O'Malley following O'Malley's publication of On Another Man's Wound. Many of the official legal documents in this series are photocopies received from the High Court of Justice in Dublin, Ireland.
  - Index to Legal, 2010 (Box 6, Folder 15A)
  - Affidavit: O'Malley Helen Hooker v. O'Malley, Ernest, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Boat Registration "Brendan Naomha" (St. Brendan), 1946 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Certificates: Birth and Death: May 27, 1897, March 25, 1957 (copies made in 1993), 1897, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Drivers License (paperwork), 1937, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Gun Permit, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Legal Brief - Abstract of Evidence in the case of Ernie O'Malley, civilian present in Military Custody, Jan 11, 1923 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Libel Action: Joe O'Doherty (re: "On Another Man's Wound) original clippings, 1936-1937 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Libel Action: Joe O'Doherty (re: "On Another Man's Wound) clippings (copies), 1936-1937 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Marriage Certificate (copy), Sept 27, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - O'Malley v. O'Malley: Judgment (Dismissal), Mar 30, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - O'Malley v. O'Malley: Summons, 1950-1951 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Will (signed copy), Marh 1957 (Box 6, Folder 26)
- Series VII. Financial, 1935-1957
  This series contains invoices, receipts, bills and correspondence from purveyors and businesses pertaining to items bought for the O'Malley household, including food, clothing, electricity, household furnishings, car repairs and books and publications. The material provides a unique and intimate look into the personal life of the O'Malley family.
  - Index to Financial, 2010 (Box 6, Folder 27A)
  - Farm Expenses, 1940-1946 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Hibernian Bank Ltd., Account Book and cover (oversize), 1940-1957 (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts I (furnishings, groceries, etc.), 1936 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts I, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Household Expenses: Bills, Invoices, Receipts, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts (with copies), 1938 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts (with copies), 1939 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts (with copies), 1940 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts I, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts II, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts I, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts II, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts I, 1944 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts II, 1944 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Income Tax Records, 1943 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Personal Expenses Ledger (Ernie O'Malley), 1954-1955 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Pension Papers, 1934-1953 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Real Estate: Carrowkeel land receipt and payment schedule, 1943-1944 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Real Estate: Map of Burrishoole Lands, circa 1941-1945 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Series VIII. Nationalistic Material, 1643-1966, undated
  Newspaper clippings, booklets, notes, pamphlets, military training manuals, reports, memorandums, photographs and other printed matter relating to the nationalist movement in Ireland. Drawn to the nationalist cause in midst of the Easter Rising in 1916, O'Malley later joined the Irish Republican Army and became a key figure in the War of Independence and Irish Civil War. Items in this series provide details of O'Malley's military career, as well as, insight into the publications and propaganda that powered the nationalist movement throughout Ireland. Also included in this series are official reports and memoranda issued by Oglaigh na hEireann, otherwise known as the Irish Republican Army. Of special interest in this series are a few items relating to O'Malley's interviews with veterans of the War of Independence and Civil War. Beginning in the early 1940s, O'Malley embarked on an ambitious effort to document first-hand accounts of both wars and as a result, hand-recorded approximately 450 interviews with his former military comrades. Most items relating to his military interviews were placed in the archives of University College Dublin in 1974, however, a limited amount of materials pertaining to the interviews remain in this series.
  Materials in this series are in two groups: military training manuals arranged chronologically and printed material arranged alphabetically.
  - Index to Nationalistic material, 2010 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Military Training Manual: Field Service Pocketbook with 1916 amendments, 1914 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Military Training Manual: Musketry Consisting of Theory of Rifle Fire 1. Elementary; 2. Advance (Forster Groom and Co., Ltd., London), 1914 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Military Training Manual: Notes on Elementary Field Training Part II (publisher: Hugh Rees Ltd., London), 1915 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Military Training Manual: Musketry Consisting of Arming Instruction and Firing Instruction by Simplex (Forster, Groom and Co., Ltd., London), 1916 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Military Training Manual: Musketry Consisting of Visual Training and Judging Distance (Forster Groom and Co., Ltd., London), 1916 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Military Training Manual: Notes for Infantry Officers on Trench Warfare, 1917 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Military Training Manual: Artillery Map Reading and Elementary Gunnery Made Easy by "Gunlayer" and "Contour" (Gale and Polden, Ltd., London), 1918 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Military Training Manual: Lewis Gun Training, 1918 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Military Training Manual: Musketry '303 and '22 Cartridges, Elementary Training, Visual Training, etc. (John Murray, London), 1918 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Military Training Manual: Bayonet Fighting for War by Captain Leopold McLaglen (Harrison and Sons, London), undated (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Military Training Manual: Oglaig na Eireann "Cyclist Training Manual, Handbook No. 7 (IRA Official Publications), undated (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Photographs: Liam Lynch, IRA Chief of Staff; Dublin Castle, circa 1936, 1936, undated (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - An tOglac: Offical organ of the Irish Volunteers Vol. 1, nos. 2 and 3, Sep 1918 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - The Constitution of the Free State of Ireland 1921 English translation (Stationery Office of Dublin), undate (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - "The Countermanding orders of Holy Week, 1916" by Diarmuid Lynch in An Cosantoir, Dublin, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 27)